Welcome to this panel for Hypertext
and Fictions at L0 26.
We have a great lineup here today.
We have Jason Boyd from Toronto
Metropolitan University, Emily Carr
from nectar, Inc., Dean Gregor
and David
Wright from University of Bergen.
Without further
ado, I will let Jason take the wheel.
And thanks so much for your time
and attention.
Right.
Thanks.
Just share my screen here.
Okay.
Going to get right into it.
So this paper starts from the premise
that electronic literature is a literary
form that is is as deserving of careful
attention and textual studies.
Is that given to literature
and other formats such as print?
It follows from this premise
that key works of electronic literature
need to be made accessible
to scholars of literature, in versions
that have been developed
in textual studies to enable deep
and sustained scholarly inquiry.
The relevant
format here is the critical edition,
a version of the literary text
that is enhanced by a scholarly apparatus
that can include collation
and annotation of textual variation
between versions
or witnesses of the literary work,
sometimes with emendations
addressing textual problems,
explanatory notes, glosses, indices,
and a critical introduction.
As a result of a comment made by
one of the anonymous reviewers
of the abstract submitted for this paper.
I feel it's necessary to point out that
the volumes of the electronic literature
collection, as excellent and important
as they are,
and Bertram and Montfort's
recent output computer generated
texts are not, to my understanding,
critical scholarly editions.
They are akin to the Norton Anthologies
of literature, which select which
these anthologies are primarily
for reading and classroom instruction,
and do not constitute
a detailed critical examination
of or engagement with the text.
They include, which is beyond
the scope of the anthology format.
So, as Ellen Gailey observed
about the Modern Language Association's
Committee on Scholarly Editions
2016 White Paper considering
the scholarly edition in the digital age,
it makes no direct mention of how editors
should face a textual condition
of the late
20, 20, and 21st centuries. Any
scholarly editor
interested in the scholarly editing
of electronic literature or video games
or ebooks,
or digital records of musical theater,
or digital republication of public domain
print texts.
Well, obviously
be working with very new kinds
of materials for textual scholarship.
Overall, the white paper
which remember is titled
considering the scholarly Edition
in the Digital Age, contains barely a hint
that we might need to edit materials
from the digital age.
So to date, and only last year has there
been produced a critical edition of a born
digital work of electronic literature.
This is the claim made by Alan Gailey,
Alan Forge and Brendan Allen,
in reference to their Aperture Science
A Critical Edition.
Although this claim should be considered
in the context of kindred efforts
such as the traversals of Dean
Gregor and Stuart Mothra, Pathfinders
Project and Dena Larson and Matthew
Kirschenbaum, recovery of William H.
Stickies, hyper poems and publication
of this work on the Internet Archive.
Also on Wednesday,
Mark sample demonstrated another
editorial model in his Very Aurum edition
of Aaron Reed's novel subcutaneous,
where the reader can study
unique tellings of the story
as generated by a custom program.
And Tim Eliza's Inventing Eliza.
The focus of a panel later today
may offer yet another model,
so Aperture Science is the companion
website to the popular and critically
acclaimed video game portal.
The site quote position visitors
as though they were using a computer
terminal in Aperture Science Laboratories,
the fictional setting for portal.
The site used flash
to simulate a door style command prompt
terminal interface, typical of computers
prior to the era
of the windowed graphical user interface.
And so we can see that here.
Aperture Science and Critical Edition
ambitiously reconstructed
or collated the witnesses comprising
the work, encoding the text of T
and using an Excel script to transform it.
This into a single twine HTML file,
which may be opened in a web browser and
which links to copies of the media files
used in the original Aperture Science.
Com website.
The critical edition was published in
2025, in volume 42 of Scholarly Editing,
the Annual of the Association
of Documentary Editing,
along with pertinent
scholarly discussions.
This edition helpfully provides the ground
from which to conceptualize
a critical editions from of other
or born digital interactive fiction.
So in this paper
I offer a conceptualization of,
or more accurately,
perhaps a series of challenges
concerning a critical edition whose object
of scholarly attention is a work
belonging to the parser
based interactive fiction genre.
Emily Schwartz Glass, a work created
using the if integrated development
environment or IDE and natural language
programing language in form seven.
The story file.
The story file, and by implication,
the source text for glass has multiple
witnesses or versions on glasses page.
On the Interactive Fiction Database,
there is a link via the Wayback Machine
to the original website, where the work
serial number is 50606060503.
The playable z z blurb file on the IFBB
has the serial number 061008,
and the updated website also via
the Wayback Machine from 2009 to 2011.
Links to story files
that are all designated, like the story
files already mentioned as version one,
but that comprise versions
with three additional serial numbers.
Finally, the IFD entry contains a latest
website link where the work is designated
version three, so we have versions labeled
one and three, but not two,
which comprised witnesses
six witnesses based on serial numbers.
So with
glass, as with other online
parser based interactive
fiction, a fundamental editorial
question is what is the work?
What is the object of critical attention
and intervention?
Is it the source text?
The text is written by the author.
Is it the story file?
The source text is compiled into a format
that can be executed
using an interpreter.
That is the playable version. Is it?
The transcript of the story is generated
during a playthrough of the work.
The challenge editorially
is that it is fundamentally all three.
The source text.
The authorial text is not the work
until it is compiled into a reader format.
The story file and in this format is.
It is, like the source text, a latent,
a potential work of literature,
only realized when it is generated
through reader interaction.
Without this
interaction, the story file as executed
by an interpreter is merely a screen
of preliminary text, followed
by a greater than sign command prompt.
So an informed seven source text
is the most immediate
and perhaps the only true authorial text.
Glasses.
Source text consists of a preamble
and six chapters,
most of which are further divided
into sections.
As a natural language programing language.
The text of the source text
is ostensibly readable
by those who read English,
but this does not mean
they will understand what they read
unless they are familiar
with the conventions of Inform
Seven's syntax.
I'll use one example
for an example from From Glasses preamble.
To illustrate the line, use no scoring
the serial comma and American dialect.
This imperative sentence, usually included
at the start of a source text,
tells the compiler what settings
the game will use in terms of punctuation
and spelling preferences.
The deletion of no scoring in version
three does not signify that this version
uses scoring,
but appears to reflect a decision
during the ongoing development of inform
seven to remove
scoring as the default feature of compiled
and form seven works,
therefore obviating the need to declare a
no scoring setting.
So how would an editor of a critical
scholarly edition deal with this example?
Both the variation between witnesses
and the impact of the statement itself
in glass source text.
Short has already extensively
annotated the file using Informed Seven's
comment notation,
enclosing your comments within square
brackets,
and an editor could add annotations
also using the comment notation
as in the example shown here.
So the
interrelationship between the source text
and the compiled story file necessitates
the development of an editorial theory,
fundamentally based on interactive fiction
status as a literary work
that is programed and played,
and much ground in this area has been
helpfully mapped out by Nick Montfort
in his monograph Twisty Little Passages.
As William Winder has noted of text
and story generation system, scholars
have to develop a poetics
that is a theory of procedural authorship,
a concept articulated by Janet H.
Murray, poetics
of how these author procedures generate
a given text, in this case
in collaboration with the reader,
and the poetics of how to read the text
that is generated,
although it is fundamentally based on it,
reading the source text
does not approximate
in any meaningful way.
The experience of reading
the story file is presented
for interaction through an interpreter.
For example, section one of chapter
two of the source text
and glass specifies
the rules by which the player character
converse with the other characters,
but this in no way resembles what
a conversation looks like as it unfolds
during the interaction with the work.
The texts are interdependent,
but hardly identical
in a non-trivial sense.
A critical edition of an.
If work is incomplete
without the input of the reader,
a realized if work is fundamentally
a textual exchange.
But there are many potential readers of an
if and thus
many possible variants of exchange.
Short has provided a walkthrough
that accounts for the varying branches
the narrative can take,
and these streamlined paths represent
an authoritative vision
of what might be called the ideal reader
who always knows the or a meaningful
input to provide in every prompt
an exceedingly rare species
to encounter in the wild.
With shorts walkthroughs, one could create
a version of the interface
designed for the critical edition
of Aperture Science,
and in this edition, the reader is able
to interact with the text, while a left
hand column provides navigational guidance
and critical annotation for each screen.
The user encounters.
However, the interactive
possibilities of Aperture Science
are much more rigidly structured
and tightly scope than glass.
There are other texts
and other reading experiences of glass
that are possible
beyond those mapped out by short, and
there are very possibly interesting texts
and reading experiences
that can be generated through interaction
that have not been anticipated by short.
Additionally,
the club Floyd as a club Floyd transcript
of the cooperative playthrough of glass
shows the exploration of a passer
based work is usually meandering,
repetitive, trial by error affair
that depends on a reader's if literacy
in tandem with the author's skill
at what Janet Murray terms
scripting the interactor
subtly directing the reader
to type meaningful inputs.
But it is very challenging for an author
and an editor to anticipate
every reasonable input and completely mad
to anticipate
every unreasonable but possible input.
So, in
his chapter on the text, adventure
and cyber text, espionage
notes that the reading experiences
of a passer based work
typically involves
the reader being addressed
by multiple voices
or multiple registers and responses.
One voice is a text written by the author
that is outputted for the reader to read,
such as the description of an object
at the reader examines another voice,
speaks the built in responses to commands
that are common or possible in
if but that are not explicitly implemented
in the work being read.
For example, that's not a verb
I recognize, or the and monetary
violence isn't the answer to this one
or the solicitous.
Are you sure you want to quit?
A third voice is an amalgam,
a customized response to an action
that would logically be
possible, but that has been
not been implemented.
It is the second built in response
that offer an editorial challenge,
because they can be
part of the reader experience, but
they are not present in the source text
as writing with informed notes.
A new, informed
project is void and without form,
so to speak, with nothing created.
But it starts with hundreds
of standard rules already in place,
including rules for built in responses.
This means that any given reading of an
if will likely includes text
that the author neither wrote
nor that is present in the source text,
which presents an editorial emendation
challenge that is quite different
from those encountered
in traditional critical editing.
As a work of parser based.
If glass must be experienced
as such in any critical encounter,
and therefore a critical edition
would have to decide a
design and apparatus that was accessible
to traverse the work, and that dynamically
responded to the inputs of the player
and the outputs of the interpreter.
In a critical edition
that the reader plays, how would one
design the critical annotation
could be functionally integrated with it?
There is, as we have
seen, the example of Aperture Science,
a critical edition with the editorial
sidebar that is separated from the text,
and that dynamically changes
as the reader traverses the work.
However, one issue with this approach
could be
that the list of possible commands
that reader would enter at any
given prompt
could be substantial and unwieldy,
depending on whether the editor
takes a prescriptive or an open
ended approach to command options, which,
like other decisions that must be made,
is ultimately a matter of defining one's
editorial theory and principles.
Other possible approaches would integrate
editorial annotation in the source text
in ways
that is accessible in the compiled story
file that is accessed by the readers
through the interpreter.
One possible approach to editorial
annotation is suggested
by the informal recipe book section
dealing,
detailing how conventional footnotes
can be included in an interactive fiction.
Another approach is suggested by my title.
The editor could implement
additional objects called things notes
in the source text that would explain
in world features and offer guidance.
Like other objects in the world,
the reader could examine
or read the notes.
One could go further and implement
a book object in the player characters
inventory
that could be consulted using its index,
following the example provided
in the informal recipe
book of an encyclopedic reference
work, Costa Rican or Anthology,
where the player can consult
named entries using commands
like lookup, quetzal, and guide.
Another possible approach
would be to customize
the helping and hinting systems
that can be built in inform
to offer guidance about possible commands,
how the program would respond.
All these approaches
would require the addition of inform
seven procedural authoring to an editors
skill set, but would be a valuable way
of exploring the affordances of a form
seven as a platform for critical scholarly
editing of interactive fiction.
In addition to its primary use
as a platform
for authoring interactive fiction.
Thank you, and I welcome any suggestions
or thoughts you might have about
conceptualizing
critical editions of interactive fiction.
Thank you. Thank you very much, Jason.